A Guide to the Charles Adam Dempsey Papers, 1866-1941
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Charles Adam Dempsey Papers, 1866-1941
The Library of Virginia
22976
12 leaves
Charles Adam Dempsey
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 15 January 1949, of Lena Lawson Dempsey, Richmond, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Charles Adam Dempsey was born 15 November 1844 in Alexandria, Virginia. He was appointed to the United States Military Academy 1 September 1861, and graduated in 1865. Dempsey was commissioned a 2nd lieutenant, then promoted to 1st lieutenant 23 June 1865 and assigned to the 17 Infantry Regiment stationed on Hart's Island in New York. He was transferred to the 35th Infantry Regiment in Texas 21 September 1866. After being transferred to the 2nd Infantry Regiment, 3 June 1870, Dempsey served in Alabama, Idaho, and Nebraska, promoted to captain 9 February 1878. Commissioned a major of infantry 26 April 1898, Dempsey served in Cuba during the Spanish-American War. Promoted to lieutenant colonel 16 June 1899, Dempsey commanded troops in the Philippines from 1900 to 1901. Appointed a colonel of infantry 4 March 1901, Dempsey retired from active service 27 September 1901. He moved to Richmond, Virginia, and was recalled to military duty with the militia of Virginia, serving from 13 October to 20 January 1922. Dempsey and his wife Lena Lawson Dempsey had one son. Dempsey died 4 June 1941 in Richmond, Virginia, and was buried in Arlington National Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1866-1941, of Charles Adam Dempsey (1844-1941) of Richmond, Virginia, consisting of commissions, 1866-1901, of Dempsey to various ranks in the United States Army. Papers also include a photograph, June 1922, of Colonel Dempsey; newspaper articles, 1940, on Dempsey as oldest living U. S. Military Academy graduate; and Dempsey's service record compiled by Major General Emory Sherwood Adams, adjutant general of the United States, 18 June 1941.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
William Worth Dempsey papers, 1916-1918 (LVA accession 23831).
Contents List
- Commission, 20 April 1866, appointing Dempsey a 1st lieutenant in the 17th Infantry Regiment of the United States Army dating from 23 June 1865, signed by President Andrew Johnson (1808-1875) and Secretary of War Edwin M. Stanton (1814-1869).
- Commission, 23 April 1866, appointing Dempsey a 2nd lieutenant in the 17th Infantry Regiment dating from 23 June 1865, signed by Johnson and Stanton.
- Commission, 11 April 1867, appointing Dempsey a 1st lieutenant in the 35th Infantry Regiment dating from 23 June 1865, signed by Johnson and Stanton.
- Commission, 27 April 1878, appointing Dempsey a captain in the 2nd Infantry Regiment dating from 9 February 1878, signed by President Rutherford B. Hayes (1822-1893) and Secretary of War George W. McCrary (1835-1890).
- Commission, 7 June 1898, appointing Dempsey a major of infantry dating from 26 April 1898, signed by President William McKinley (1843-1901) and Secretary of War, Russell A. Alger (1836-1907).
- Commission, 26 December 1899, appointing Dempsey a lieutenant colonel of infantry dating from 16 June 1899, signed by McKinley and Secretary of War Elihu Root (1845-1937).
- Commission, 11 March 1901, appointing Dempsey a colonel of infantry dating from 4 March 1901, signed by McKinley and Root.
- Photograph, June 1922, of Colonel Dempsey.
- Two newspaper articles, 1940, on Dempsey as oldest living U. S. Military Academy graduate.
- Dempsey's service record compiled 18 June 1941 by Major General Emory Sherwood Adams, adjutant general of the United States.